Finding aid for the Getty Education Institute, Art Education History Archives Project, 1998-1999 IA20034
Institutional Records and Archives
Art Education History Archives project
1998-1999
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Education Institute for the Arts
Dobbs, Stephen M.
IA20034
3.6 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
The records consist of a Getty Education Institute sponsored program to video-record interviews with leading art educators of the 1980s and 1990s. The resulting 45 VHS cassette recordings and transcriptions produced during 1998 and 1999, document the ideas and programs of the Getty Center for Education in the Arts, later known as the Getty Education Institute, that helped shape contemporary arts education in the United States.
Related Archival Materials note
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the people, programs, and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Getty Institutional Archives
Senior Program Officer Stephen M. Dobbs' records, 1984-1989, Getty Center for Education in the Arts. Institutional Archives, Research Library, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA20027
Director Lani Duke's Records, 1986-1998, Getty Education Institute. Institutional Archives, Research Library, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA10015
Event and publication images, 1985-1997, Getty Education Institute. Institutional Archives, Research Library, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA20018
Acquisition Information
One copy of the Art Education History Archives project records was provided to Dr. Stephen M. Dobbs upon completion of the Getty Education Institute commissioned project. Dr. Dobbs held these records until August 14, 2008 when he transferred them to the Institutional Archives. Accession no. 2008.IA.31.
Restrictions on Access
The transcripts described in accession 2008.IA.31 are available for use by qualified researchers. The original transcripts and videocassettes are restricted for preservation purposes.
Online digital copies exist for the transcripts. Where use copies do not exist, production of use copies is required before access will be granted; this may delay research requests. Advanced notice is required. Transcripts and recordings are restricted to on-site use only.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
The records consist of a Getty Education Institute sponsored program to video-record interviews with leading art educators of the 1980s and 1990s. The interviews provide an intellectual record of these educators' views of and participation with the Getty Center for Education in the Arts, later known as the Getty Education Institute. At a time when the J. Paul Getty Trust was the primary force in improving art education at every grade level (K-12) throughout the United States, the project provides insights into the ideas and programs that helped shape the contemporary arts education field. The records include a biographical and philosophical glimpse into such leading minds as Elliot Eisner, Edmund Feldman, Kenneth Marantz, Brent Wilson, and Harold Williams.
Dr. Stephen M. Dobbs was commissioned by the Getty Education Institute in 1998 to conduct, record and transcribe these interviews. The first interviews were begun on April 2, 1998 and the project was completed on May 12, 1999. The collection consists of a complete set of 45 VHS cassette recordings and corresponding transcripts. Each interview runs approximately 60 minutes. The transcripts have been digitized.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by type of material and then alphabetically by the surname of the interviewee.
Administrative History
The Getty Center for Education in the Arts, later known as the Getty Education Institute for the Arts (GEI), was one of the original programs established by the J. Paul Getty Trust, an international cultural and philanthropic organization serving both general audiences and specialized professionals. The Trust is a not-for-profit institution, educational in purpose and character, that focuses on the visual arts in all of their dimensions. As of 2009 the Trust supports and oversees four programs: the J. Paul Getty Museum, the Getty Foundation, the Getty Conservation Institute, and the Getty Research Institute. The Trust founded the Getty Center for Education in the Arts in 1982 with the mission of improving the quality and status of arts education in the nation's public schools. The education programs were guided by three premises: the visual arts should be an essential part of every child's education because knowledge of the arts is a principal means of understanding human experiences and transmitting cultural values; art education's content must be broadened to include instruction in art production, art history, art criticism, and aesthetics—an approach known as discipline-based art education (DBAE); and the most effective art education programs are based on partnerships among teachers, administrators, artists, museums, universities, and parents.
During its first ten years, the Getty Center for Education in the Arts / GEI concentrated on the implementation and dissemination of DBAE. This was achieved by advocating for the value of arts in education, through the dissemination of print publications and videotapes, national conferences, and collaborative projects; professional development for school and university personnel, through in-service programs such as the Los Angeles Institute; theory development to encourage evolution of DBAE, through seminars, doctoral fellowships, and the commissioning of scholarly publications; curriculum development to support creation of model instructional materials; and special initiatives to encourage others to champion DBAE. In January 1986 responsibility for administering arts education grants was transferred from the Trust's Grant Program to the Center for Education in the Arts. The goal of the arts education grant program was to support the development of model DBAE programs across the country.
Lani Duke was the founding director of the Getty Center for Education in the Arts / GEI and continued to lead the program for 17 years. Duke resigned at the end of June, 1998 upon notice of the GEI's imminent dissolution. President Barry Muntiz named Ted Mitchell, former dean of the UCLA School of Education, as the Getty Trust's Vice President for Education and interim director of the Education Institute until the program's dissolution in 1999.
When the Getty Education Institute for the Arts was dissolved one of its last projects was to record the legacy of its programs, most specifically the DBAE program, through interviews with leading arts educators of the time. The Center for Education in the Arts commissioned Dr. Stephen M. Dobbs in 1998 to conduct, record and transcribe these interviews. The project was completed in June 1999.
Technical Requirements
Access to digital files is available online through the links provided in the inventory. Due to rights restrictions, some online recordings are available to on-site researchers only.
Use copies do not exist for all recordings in this collection. The production of use copies is required before access can be granted and may add a delay to research requests.
Art in education -- United States -- 20th century; Art -- Study and teaching -- United States -- 20th century; Educators -- Interviews; Videocassettes; Transcripts; Arts -- Education, Elementary; Electronic records (digital records); Williams, Harold Marvin, 1928-; Getty Education Institute for the Arts; Wilson, Brent; Marantz, Kenneth A.; Feldman, Edmund Burke; Eisner, Elliot W.; J. Paul Getty Trust; Getty Center for Education in the Arts
- Art Education History Archives project, 1998-1999
  - Transcripts of interviews, 1998-1999
    - List of interviewees, June 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 1)
    - Gordon Ambach, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 2)
    - Neil Anstead, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 3)
    - Terry Barrett, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 4)
    - Candice Borland, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 5)
    - Diane Brigham, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 6)
    - Sheila Brown, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 7)
    - Judith Burton, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 8)
    - Laura Chapman, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 9)
    - Eleanor Chow, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 10)
    - Gilbert Clark, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 11)
    - Lila Crespin, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 12)
    - Jack Davis, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 13)
    - Michael Day, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 14)
    - Leilani Duke, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 15)
    - Phillip Dunn, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 16)
    - Elliot Eisner, April 28, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 17)
    - Mary Erickson, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 18)
    - Edmund Feldman, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 19)
    - Virginia Gembica, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 20)
    - Joseph Goldyne, April 28, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 21)
    - Richard Gurin, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 22)
    - Thomas Hatfield, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 23)
    - Al Hurwitz, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 24)
    - Catherine Leffler, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 25)
    - Anne Lindsey, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 26)
    - Peter London, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 27)
    - Jesse Lovano-Kerr, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 28)
    - Marshall Lumsden, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 29)
    - Stanley Madeja, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 30)
    - Kenneth Marantz, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 31)
    - Val Marmillion, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 32)
    - Pamela Ann Marton, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 33)
    - Bruce Newlin, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 34)
    - Karen Newlin, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 35)
    - Jeffery Patchen, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 36)
    - Joan Peterson, May 12, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 37)
    - Bonnie Pitman, May 12, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 38)
    - Martin Rosenberg, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 39)
    - Vicki Rosenberg, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 40)
    - Blanche Rubin, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 41)
    - Ronald Silverman, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 42)
    - Mark Slavkin, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 43)
    - Mary Ann Stankiewicz, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 44)
    - Harold Williams, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 45)
    - Brent Wilson, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-1, Folder 46)
  - Video recordings of interviews, 1998-1999; VHS cassettes
    - Gordon Ambach, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 1)
    - Neil Anstead, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 2)
    - Terry Barrett, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 3)
    - Candice Borland, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 4)
    - Diane Brigham, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 5)
    - Sheila Brown, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 6)
    - Judith Burton, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 7)
    - Laura Chapman, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 8)
    - Eleanor Chow, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 9)
    - Gilbert Clark, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 10)
    - Lila Crespin, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 11)
    - Jack Davis, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 12)
    - Michael Day, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 13)
    - Leilani Duke, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 14)
    - Phillip Dunn, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 15)
    - Elliot Eisner, April 28, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 16)
    - Mary Erickson, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 17)
    - Edmund Feldman, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 18)
    - Virginia Gembica, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 19)
    - Joseph Goldyne, April 28, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 20)
    - Richard Gurin, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 21)
    - Thomas Hatfield, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 22)
    - Al Hurwitz, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 23)
    - Catherine Leffler, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 24)
    - Anne Lindsey, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 25)
    - Peter London, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 26)
    - Jesse Lovano-Kerr, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 27)
    - Marshall Lumsden, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 28)
    - Stanley Madeja, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 29)
    - Kenneth Marantz, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 30)
    - Val Marmillion, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 31)
    - Pamela Ann Marton, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-2, Folder 32)
    - Bruce Newlin, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 33)
      Scope and Contents
      Pages 16 and 17 missing from transcript
    - Karen Newlin, October 10, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 34)
    - Jeffery Patchen, March 26, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 35)
    - Joan Peterson, May 12, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 36)
    - Bonnie Pitman, May 12, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 37)
    - Martin Rosenberg, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 38)
    - Vicki Rosenberg, April 4, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 39)
    - Blanche Rubin, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 40)
    - Ronald Silverman, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 41)
    - Mark Slavkin, October 9, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 42)
    - Mary Ann Stankiewicz, April 2, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 43)
    - Harold Williams, January 14, 1999 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 44)
    - Brent Wilson, April 3, 1998 (Box 2008.IA.31-3, Folder 45)